welcome to the active inference
institute this is the participatory
online laboratory today is tuesday
september 13th and we are here with
mathstream 4.1
uh with david spivak and we are welcome
to take any questions in the youtube
chat so if you have any questions please
write them there and we will have time
to
ask our presenter during the course of
this discussion uh david is here to talk
to us today about dynamic interfaces and
arrangements an algebraic framework for
interacting systems
please take it away
okay yeah thanks a lot for having me um
so i i'm gonna talk for around 40
minutes but for maybe almost an hour i
don't know
but feel free to interrupt um with
whatever and i wanted to say at the
offset that
i'm not really talking much about um
active inference
itself here i'm mainly saying like
another perspective on interacting
systems or systems that might learn or
something like that and i'm more like
waiting for the discussion time to kind
of find these links
so um
yeah
okay so i want to talk about
dynamic interfaces and arrangements and
what that means and this applied
category theory point of view on things
so
so why am i here
um i'm here to seek a valuable exchange
of ideas because active inference offers
first time i heard about it it's
compelling and most people apparently
find it unusual but for some reason it
instantly meshed with my own intuition
about things that i've gotten from
applied category theory and so i think
there's a lot we can learn from each
other
so applied category theory emphasizes
structure rather than quantitative
analysis so most of math and science
today reduce all of our experience to
plays of quantity so you have graphs and
you have numbers
and um you measure things in numbers and
you have probabilities and those are
numbers and so everything is just a
number but experience what's happening
now i mean what number would you put on
you know the sound of my voice or the or
what numbers you could put numbers on
this slide but would they tell you what
the slide was about
and so
what category theory emphasizes it's
still math but it emphasizes structure
it emphasizes relations between things
like the relationship between what's on
this slide and other things on the slide
and which one the rest of the talk the
relationship between that and me the
relationship between that and you and
the kind of coherence between all that
like why are we really here what is it
um how does it cohere how did it come
together so applied category theory aims
to bring that math to relational
disciplines outside of math
so i want to tell you about applied
category theory specifically in
reference to interfaces because i'm
going to say that we interact through
our interfaces when you hear the word
interface you might think markov blanket
i don't know enough to be sure that
that's exactly what i mean so that's
kind of where this is fitting in maybe
into active inference framing but i'd
rather you just think about interfaces
um so i'm asking in this talk what sort
of algebra could support us
in thinking about
interaction and stuff like that
um i think of mathematical fields as
accounting systems
so um i like that the word count is in
there and i like how kind of
humble it is it's like an accounting
system here
so if you want to um
if you have arithmetic that's a
mathematical field and it accounts for
the flow of quantities like in finance
so if you want to your accountant to
help you say why you did what you did or
what you did and how the quantities
flowed you would write something in an
arithmetic account you'd write an
arithmetic account of it you'd say and
they could someone could point that and
say what's this 12.83 cents and you
could explain so there's numbers and you
can account for stuff
what if you wanted to account for
the
teleportation protocol of quantum
mechanics or something like that
so hilbert spaces is a is a branch of
math and it helps you make accounts for
the sorts of things that people do in
quantum computing or quantum mechanics
or generally
probability distributions is a
mathematical field but it helps you
account for likelihoods why is somebody
winning in poker and somebody not
if you want to give that account and you
want to be careful about it you'd use
probability distributions
so but what is an account of phenomena
like we're already kind of talking and
you know somebody might give an account
of their finances or something and just
written in english
but you can't really be that careful
with it you can't track it
you can't be sure you know what they're
saying and that you can point at
something so the language the accounting
system has to articulate the relevant
type differences
and provide operations that correspond
with their interactions and that's
really a dense statement um i didn't
mean to i'm trying to keep things
concise but what do i mean there in in
accounting for dollars and like
financial stuff
there's dollars and there's numbers of
things and there and you can add and
subtract dollars like this was five
dollars and he paid four so there's one
dollar left so you can subtract them or
add them but you can't multiply two
dollar figures it doesn't mean anything
to multiply five dollars times eight
dollars but you can multiply five
dollars by eight things like so i sold
eight things of five dollars each so the
operations that you're allowed to do
um
there are different type differences
there's the number of widgets and then
there's the price of the widgets and
that's a difference in type and the
operations make sense with plus you're
allowed to add dollars and you're
allowed to add numbers of widgets but
you're not allowed to multiply uh
numbers of dollars by numbers of dollars
so that's kind of what i mean here an
accounting system needs to tell you like
hey that's not what dollars means what
would it even mean to multiply five
dollars by eight dollars
um is it in dollars squared now or
something anyway so that's the sort of
thing an accounting system does it gives
you the um
a way of knowing what you're allowed to
do what the type differences are and
what you can operate how you operate on
them so category if every mathematical
field is an accounting system then
category theory is an accounting system
so what is an accounting system for it's
an accounting system for the fact that
we see in the world coherent structures
we see in the world flows of things we
see in the world quantum mechanics we
see in the world likelihoods and we see
in the world coherent structures so if
we want to account for them we need some
language and the one that's been
invented is category theory
and so it makes analogies which are
similarities of structure with different
content
um
i've got one thing and another thing a
is to be a c is to d
that similarity is made into a formal
object
and category theory has been useful in
math in computer science physics
materials science linguistics
um and moreover one thing i didn't see
on the slide is that category theory
helps you invent new mathematical fields
they might not be big ones that are
studied by a million people you might
just have a micro
custom built
accounting system
written in category theory so you make a
new system of structure and what i'm
interested in is what sort of system
accounting system would could be used to
account for dynamic interaction
like things interacting
so the driving question
i really prefer to have a question that
i can always be asking instead of one
that i need very specific lab to do so i
want to know what we have right here
i want to account for this incredible
world that we have because on earth we
have all these amazing forms of life
from cells to humans
like how did that come about and we have
the built world where we have
transportation systems and things like
that and we have computers it's an
amazing built world we have language the
ability to systematically present
knowledge like a slideshow or a history
book or whatever
we have morality with rules of thumb for
living a good life how did that come
about i think in each of these cases
they evolved through the push and pull
and struggle of living so
language is refined by continually using
language and the way we present
knowledge or the built world the way we
architect things um
is continually evolving and in even
morality like you have a bunch of
societies that have to live together and
they evolve a way to do that so i want
to see
see all that um i want to account for
that
so what are these systems and how they
develop and how do we talk about them
all at once um
what language is appropriate for giving
accounts of this happening in action
um and can we use that language to
engineer new systems
and then something we were talking about
just before we started the talk today is
like what constitutes health or wisdom
what gives the system a sense of
direction and how come it keeps finding
good senses of direction in the sense
that evolution
somehow our civilization is offering
more today than it did
in the past
so the only part of this i'm going to
discuss is the potential accounting
system that i'm offering here or like
the beginning of it
so um
in other words i don't know how all this
stuff happened
i just and i don't want to be the one to
figure out all the how this stuff
happened because obviously it's more
than even
then you know any group of people could
really finish or even and i don't even
have the capacity to really start
but i think there are many people who do
and already are doing that and all i'm
trying to offer is a way we could put
that into some sort of accounting system
okay
so this this thing we're doing now is
the subject of the talk it's dynamic
interaction
morphology the way that things form like
topos institute formed or a person forms
and behavior all that stuff is about
little systems that interact and this
interaction structure itself changes
through time and i'll explain a
mathematical language for working with
that sort of thing but on some level
much of this talk will be a case of its
own subject matter
in the sense that um
i'm interested in the development of the
life's order like what is how does this
develop but in the science system
um this takes place between the
interaction between fields so right now
uh
you guys know much more about active
inference and i know more about category
theory and so we're participating in
this science system where we're
interacting and we're having dynamic
interaction because after
this the part where i'm just talking i'm
still looking at blue as she's she's
looking at me and i'm seeing her nod and
that that helps me decide what to say
next and whether we're
where um how this communication is
working so we're experiencing the
development the the ability for systems
interacting to shape you know shape that
interaction and become
sent like sense make together um in real
time here
so the the concepts discussed in this
talk should describe the talk itself as
an interaction so let me just pause for
feedback and just kind of get someone
else's voice into the space if you're
willing uh do you see like kind of what
i'm saying that the math i'm doing i'm
talking about here should be capable i'm
not going to give the description
because i would be like filling out the
spreadsheet with all the facts but it's
more like that the map could offer the
sort of spreadsheet you would need to
talk about this sort of thing
so definitely like math related to
interaction is really what active
inference is all about and
fundamentally describes like
sense and perception and action um
daniel joined us for a minute do you
have any extra comments i have a feeling
you have something to say here
no
i would just ask uh what can math
describe and where do art
science and other things that are not
math also play roles how do those
interact
great yeah
um
cool so
i'm suggesting that math gives you the
accounting system and that science fills
it in
but let me um
yeah
yeah so i think i'm going to go into
that a little more but so there's a
self-reflective character where i'm
saying that um
you guys just actually participated in
an interaction with me and like give a
kind of sense of direction for this
talk a little bit or or at least um
one thing we want to discuss which is
what's matt what's the role of math and
science and so we're kind of
creating co-creating
uh this sense-making work that we're
doing here through our interaction and
so that's kind of what i'm saying is
that there's a self-reflective thing
that the talk itself if you want to you
can always dive into this itself as a
case
um so that's kind of hanging around but
i'm not going to push really into that
the fact that we're building something
together here too much more
uh but it's here
so
i i want to talk about how theory
compresses and
information and then and there's
elaboration and there's feedback from
experiment um so i think that
compression and elaboration play a big
role in this story we compress our past
into a form that we elaborate in the
present so we're constantly forming
memories that are not as big as the
thing that their memory of but there are
compressions that we can elaborate in
the present
dna for example compresses a record of
who died and who thrived in some sense
into a language of four nuclear types
and um theory any theory is a
compression of past experience so the
free energy principle is someone has
compressed ideas about what they've seen
over and over and over again
into a very small form
and then whether you're talking about
dna or memories or the free energy
principle these are elaborated in the
present so as i speak this theory about
compression or whatever not very
original but it's here um
that is an elaboration of something that
compressed into these slides in the past
where dna is
somehow read by
messenger rna and i don't know there's a
ribosome involved and stuff and it's
elaborated those genes are producing
proteins and those proteins are
elaborated to
um
are the elaborations that compressed
code and they then create the living
form of the thing so that seems really
important and then similarly experiment
in theory if theory is like compression
and experiments like elaboration these
exist both in biological and
mathematical fields so
almost everyone knows everyone who knows
a biology is knows that there's
experiments involved but maybe you
wouldn't think that math has
experimentation and i think that it does
but it's the attempts to articulate and
compute things that's how you that's how
you are elaborated you talk about things
and you compute and we value a formalism
f if it makes expression and computation
easy so that's the experiment like how
good is this thing well does it make it
easy to say what i want it doesn't make
it easy to compute
so with roman numerals here like i don't
think this is very good at expressing
but i know it's really bad at computing
so if you want to multiply this
roman numeral by this roman numeral
you're just kind of screwed um there's
no procedure you can go through and the
only procedure i know is to translate
them into hindi arabic numerals 14 and 6
for example and then use what these are
built for which is using the
distributive law
so 14 is 10 plus 4
and um 10 times 6 is easy and 4 times 6
is easy so you get uh 84 and so you
translate it back into lxxiv but where
that l came from
or why there are three x's you'll never
figure out
it's just 84.
so the hindi arabic numerals i'm saying
are empirically better like they just
win games right like fibonacci not only
came up with a one one two three five
eight sequence
but
probably more importantly was the one
who brought the hindi arabic numerals so
the
hindus apparently invented them and the
arabs saved them for a long time and
then fibonacci found them and brought
them to to the west and um they're just
better they just won
they just went out
and that's the way that experiment
exists in math
how easy it is to use
and that's the sort of value claim i'm
making about what i'm discussing today
that it's it's a single accounting
system you're not constantly changing
what the notation means or um
uh changing um how you're thinking about
things it's all one
system and it just works really well
with itself
so the plan for the talk is that it'll
be in four parts um i'll give a
presently available case the thing i'm
trying to model i'll give a whirlwind
tour of what the math actually looks
like i'll talk about some existing
applications and open questions and then
i'll conclude with the summary
okay so the current dynamic arrangement
so this zoom call that we're having
right now and maybe with the youtube
live stream and the people on the chat
etc is a dynamic arrangement so how do
we think about it
i want to break it into three structures
um
interfaces dynamics and interactions so
i'm going to have like
i think overall six keywords and these
are three of them and i'm sorry there
are so many but they all are different
um
so each one of us has an interface so
it's what i can express and take in i'm
expressing through the changes of my
vocal cords and the movement of my hands
and i'm taking in information through
the sensations of my body and my eyes
and my ears and then each one of us has
dynamics so i have some internal state
that you can't see exactly
uh but i'm in having in some mood and
i'm expecting to read and all that sort
of stuff and then that's updated by
what i see you guys doing or
what i'm reading on the screen
and then between us there's interaction
which is how my outputs my expression
affects you and how your expression
affects me
so those are
what i think is going on a lot of what's
going on in this dynamic arrangement
between us
it's it's really useful to draw
boundaries around things so you
modularize by nesting reference frames
um we have little we reference frames
all i mean by that i don't necessarily
mean the thing they mean in relativity
theory
although i think that would be a case a
reference frame is just a
box you put around things and you say i
can refer to this as alice and this says
bob and stuff like that i want a frame
where i get to have a notation or a way
to refer to things and we have littler
systems interacting within bigger
systems
um
all the time we could say that uh atom
with its you know um
electron orbitals or whatever is some
kind of
uh reference frame
or so but atoms are even molecules we
could think of the molecule the
reference frame for all of its atoms you
can point to them and refer to them
organizations and societies we
modularize and we say that's a thing
that's a thing that's a thing and we are
putting things together and that's
useful in evolution so for example um
according to herbert simon like that's
how evolution is so fast is because it
modularizes our liver and our stomach
and let them evolve independently
um
but also
or various systems um circulatory or
nervous system etc but also uh it's
useful in the way we think humans think
about things
i i want to emphasize again that the map
here will not be numerical it'll be
structural so as we move into the map
you'll see how it manages these
reference frames and so like geometry is
about shapes
geometry doesn't have much number in it
but there are numbers a little bit
there's like how big the angle is and
how big the sides are but it's really
about the shapes and the congruences and
stuff like that and similarly you can
put cat you can put numbers into
category theory it accepts that but it's
really about the structure of why you're
using those numbers and which numbers
can be added to other numbers or what
what the rules are about the numbers and
really you don't need numbers at all the
relationships that are happening here
for example are not numerical
um but before we get there let's make
sure we understand our principle subject
because
we'd like this map to be able to
describe things we work with like cells
or tadpoles or us or
institutes or whatever
um
and soon i'll i'll define what i mean by
interface as a mathematical object
but i want to ground this talk and
something we can all think about
together and since we don't have cells
or tadpoles here um we're the subject so
this this
this um zoom call let's say and with the
live stream and all that is the subject
how do we think about ourselves well
each one of us can do certain things and
receive certain things
okay so i can move and listen we each
outwardly express and take in what what
we what we do there um
with what i'm calling our interface as i
said before and i'm going to call these
things we the blue will always be the
things we can do so it's like the
positions of my body
and the green will be what i can take in
kind of like what's force the forces
that act on me or the sensorium i have
um
that acts on me so any expression
whether it's a sound or attitude is a
kind of position it's a position i'm
taking and kind of popular like parlance
or whatever someone's expressing
themselves or taking a position but you
could also imagine the position of my
vocal chords uh moving around and that
that movement of position is an
expression that comes out as sound
your inner states are reflected
outwardly as these positions it's
happening maybe faster than you can
recognize in the case of vocal chords
but it's still um an expression
using the blue the positions the outward
expression and then the world impinges
on you or and me and it directs me and
it moves me by forces so when i see
um
you know there could be little forces on
me or you could just say hey would you
mind passing the salt and that impinges
on me it directs me to pass the salt it
moves me maybe i don't do it but at
least it changes my internal state to
being
being stubborn or something or to being
helpful
so what your body can receive in a
moment this is a kind of weird one i'm
not going to emphasize it that much
especially later but but it's true
i think that what your body can receive
in a moment depends on its position so
when your eyes are open the type of
thing you can get in through your eyes
is bigger than when your eyes are closed
so more can act on you if i close my
eyes i just won't know what you're what
you're doing
um and when your car goes through a
tunnel the gps stops receiving
and when you unplug your monitor um from
your computer it's no longer
or your keyboard is no longer receiving
things so the position
can affect
what it can receive
the monitor is no longer receiving from
the computer if you disconnect
so the story so far is that you output
blue positions and you
p-l-u-e and you input um
forces
and so
the force
and or sensation or input that you
receive changes your internal state
and then your state is reflected
outwardly as a new position i move my
eyes or my head or or my voice box and a
new sense so and then if i close my eyes
open my eyes i have this whatever
happens
it may be the same
space of sensations or different but i
see new sensations and those uh change
my internal state etc etc so this is
repeat loops repeatedly either
discretely if you want to model it that
way or continuously
but then where do these forces inputs
come from
uh they come from this interaction so
the way that we're arranged here i'm
calling it an arrangement that's going
to be another keyword
zoom arranges it
so that my outputs get to you as inputs
so you can hear me and if um as you
receive what i say your body shifts and
that's your output and that comes to me
so
the way this works is based on the
arrangement that we're calling zoom and
so now we have another color orange and
the program arranges it so we can put
each other's outputs
and our interaction with the program may
change the arrangement itself so if
daniel wanted to he could spotlight me
or mute me
or change how the information is passed
and so
the very things that you're doing the
outputs that daniel is doing or me i
could ask him to do that or i could mute
myself the part of our outputs have the
ability to change the arrangement
between us um we can walk away or
whatever
you don't have to actually view me i
don't know why you're smiling but i'm
imagining you doing some uh practical
joke or something
um
okay so i'm going to move into the
math now um
yeah
okay so this algebraic theory of
interfaces and arrangements there's a
bunch of keywords we're going to use
and here are the six i think one two
three four five six oh seven interfaces
which in uh positions forces states
arrangements enclosures nesting okay i
don't think i've said all of them so far
but they shouldn't be too bad at this
point so we each have an interface it's
what we can it's that through which we
interact our interfaces allows ourselves
to express ourselves outward to our
position
and given a position our interface
allows us to receive certain forces or
sensations
our state is changed by the by the
received force
and then our state is expressed as a
position so where state changes based on
what we see and then we express it and
then multiple interfaces interact
together via their current arrangement
how we're arranged together it doesn't
have to be spatial arrangement we are
the three of us here on the zoom call
are arranged i guess in space but really
more importantly in terms of how zoom
wants to arrange us
and we also interact with our enclosure
which is the thing outside is another
interface and these arrangements can be
nested hierarchically so here's a
picture and it's a kind of schematic
it's not supposed to be what we really
are but every box here is an interface
so i have one two three four five
but i also have y one as an interface y
two is an interface and a z is an
interface
and the way
way i wanna draw it is that um
the interfaces each interface has on the
right i'm gonna draw the positions
the outputs so this thing is pushing out
stuff to the right
and on the left it's inputting forces or
directions so maybe this is me here and
i'm
seeing through my eyes and i'm
outputting some visual signal and i'm
outputting some auditory signal and then
somebody else
is receiving that auditory signal
and seeing some other thing and that
other person is saying something and
doing something okay so each box will
have the positions it can be on the left
on the right sorry and the inputs or
sensations or forces on the left
and my outputs become things that
force you or direct you or push you or
um are input to you
if we're connected like this
uh so
inside of each box you could imagine
there's a state and it's changing based
on what's coming in from the left-hand
wires
so inside of each box is a state
and it's it's being affected by what's
the left and it's pushing out data on
the right
and then
the multiple interfaces are interacting
together in this arrangement so y1 is
supposed to be the outer box here this
middle-sized red box is y1 the
arrangement is this formation of wires
here
um
this y1 thing is the enclosure it is
enclosing these three things like topos
institute encloses some workers inside
of it or i enclose um some some organs
inside of me or something like that
and then these arrangements finally can
be nested hierarchically so there's me
and there's you and then we're
communicating but inside of us is more
stuff and then we're forming this zoom
call z
okay i hope all that
terminology is making sense and feels
natural
the thing i didn't say here and is very
hard to draw is that the arrangements
can change through time based on what
flows within them so if i say hey please
mute me or something like that it might
change the arrangement so that you're no
longer receiving
um from me so the arrangement can change
your time based on what flows at the end
of this call when we say goodbye it will
change the arrangement
um
okay so now we're really moving into the
math so as we said an interface consists
of two things a set of positions
maybe i can be in three positions a b or
c
or maybe i have 44 real numbers worth of
positions i'm just outputting this
gigantic
44 dimensional vector constantly or
something but whatever you the point is
to make an accounting system so you can
model what you think
uh are being what the positions are
maybe you can
you can decide for yourself what set of
positions uh a being
being of type a could have
what set of positions being of type b
could have
so secondly for every position there's a
set of forces f f bracket i
or inputs
you could call the censorium it's what
can arrive when you're in that position
if you're a protein and you're folded up
maybe you just can't receive certain
things on your interior you don't
receive charge but when you're unfolded
you're receiving charge
or if you're a hedgehog
as
uh toby smythe says when you're folded
up you can't receive stuff on your belly
or something
okay so um so what we'll encode this as
a polynomial in a single variable y
uh why
why because it stands for yoneta in
category theory and because it doesn't i
don't know somehow it's kind of
makes you realize this isn't your
standard polynomial it's not an x but i
don't know i just use y it's traditional
for me at this point and this is going
to be a polynomial with non-negative
coefficients when you think of
polynomials you might think about
numbers and like x squared of 5 is 25
and stuff like that but i'm not going to
be plugging in numbers into these
polynomials they're really just ways of
housing
the data structure or like what we're
going to want to work with so i know
it's strange but it works really well
and it's formal and i don't freak out
when you see the sum sign because even
though i'm showing you the math i'm not
intending for you to like completely
follow it or need it it's an accounting
system but like fibonacci coming to the
west like you might not
you know be able to use it right away
but but if you're interested you'll you
could learn
so an interface might be that this would
be the whole interface it'd be a set of
positions p
and this dummy variable y that's always
just going to be there because it kind
of holds the place for this exponent
and the exponent
in the position i is the set of forces
you can get in position i
so now we've made math for this
interface thing which has positions and
for every position a set of forces
that can depend on the position whether
your eyes are closed or open etc
so imagine the interface was
the sum of y to the fifth
y cubed y cubed by cube 62 times y to
the zero out of zero you add all those
up
that would have one position that had
five inputs so this sensorium when the
person's in this position would be five
possible distinctions they could make
whereas in these 62 positions they could
run around these 62 and be
you would watch them running around here
and every time you know they are
receiving three
um possible distinctions as inputs
whereas when they're over here they're
receiving five when they're over here
they're receiving zero they
they can't receive ever they can't
receive
um here's another polynomial r cubed y
to the r to the million
it it
satisfies this thing these don't have to
be finite sets so in this thing it it's
positions it runs around r3 so now it's
running around not only on the surface
of the earth but it's just running
around wherever it wants to in some kind
of fixed coordinate system of the world
of the universe and at any point no
matter where it is it's always receiving
exactly a million
um
inputs so maybe
it's receiving a thousand by thousand
image it's got some so that's what it's
receiving but you just make your own
it's an accounting system for you to
make your own thing
your own interface and you can make as
many as you want so why why do all this
craziness with polynomials because
what's amazing to me is that the
polynomial operations mean things in
terms of interfaces we can add
polynomials you know how to do that
you can multiply polynomials you might
remember you do some kind of people call
it foil
you just kind of multiply the
polynomials you can compose two
polynomials
like p of q but then there's some
operations you probably haven't heard of
like tensor and or and internal harm
and these are just
um
these are what are called monoidal
structures on an aminoid closure on
a category polynomials and i'm not
telling you what that means
uh if you know some category theory you
can look at it you know already what it
means um
but uh
but they all mean something to us in
terms of what you can do to interfaces
and i'm just repeating this interface
here so if i had one of these called p
and you had one of these called q you
could add them you could multiply them
you could compose them etc
so suppose p and q are polynomials
representing two different interfaces
then
what's p plus q well it's another it's
another polynomial so it again
represents an interface
and it would be the sort it would be the
interface that can output a position of
p or of q
and it's sensorium in a given position
is whichever if it's a position of p it
would be the sensorium of that thing or
the force is there and if it's a
position of q it'd be the sensorium or
forces that you can get there
so if p was this
interface this kind of thing that output
these sorts of positions and input these
sorts of forces and q is this one then p
plus q is what nine y to the fifth plus
two y to the fourth plus y cubed and
that would be like a machine that can be
either in one of these three states or
one of these three six states and uh
sorry um positions and when they are
they'd be inputting five possible
distinctions
uh or one of these two inputting four
possible distinctions etc
so um
that's what p plus q represents it's
somehow
um making a new interface but p times q
represents making a new interface in a
different way
uh
something with this interface would
output both opposite you have to like
remember how you multiply
polynomials but basically the sum ends
of the product polynomial a sum end of
this thing is a sum end of p
and a sum end of q
so the positions of this thing
would be a pair consisting of position
of p and a position of q
but an input there or a sensation or
distinction you can make there would be
one of either p or q because like just
if you remember like what if p was 5y to
the fourth
outputs five different things and it
puts four no matter what and q is six y
cubed
outputting six and inputting three then
when you multiply them you would
output 30 i'm just multiplying straight
across here 30 y to the seventh so you
output both
a position in p and a position in q a
position in this five by six grid here
uh
and then you'd input one of seven things
either something to p or something to q
that's just what times does
you could say well i want to input to
both of them i don't want to input to
just one or the other
and then you're using a different
operation called tensor so p tensor q
takes these two things and multiplies
both positions and the directions or and
the sensoria um and lets you
output both and input both all the time
so this operation does that times
operation does one i said plus operation
does that composition is an interesting
one when you compose polynomials what it
would do is an output would be something
that
output a p
and then also a strategy for no matter
what the p input was and output of q it
doesn't it doesn't have to wait for you
to tell it
what the input to p was it'll just
give you the strategy for automatically
outputting a q thing once you know an
input
so it runs p then q in series and then
yeah and so it uh this thing kind of
outputs a protocol but i think i'm going
to say that on the next slide a little
better so um or pretty soon the or
operation runs either p or q or both in
parallel and then this bracket operation
um runs arrangements for wiring p and q
uh if you remember what that means like
i'll get into this a little more but
this one is going to output
arrangements of p in q
and input what flows on the wires um so
that's going to be an interesting one
for us later
all i'm really saying is that all these
different operations take interfaces and
make new interfaces out of them and that
allows you to
kind of build things up modularly
um we're also going to be able to we can
also formalize the notion of arrangement
so
we thought about ourselves in the zoom
call as an arrangement because zoom lets
my outputs be your inputs and vice versa
but you could also think about cells and
organs and or cells or cell organs um
arranged in a cell or cells in a tissue
uh
the arrangement is just how the
information passes between those
interfaces i'm not so concerned about
the spatial arrangement except as it
allows information to pass between the
interfaces
so here's a picture again and the orange
thing of the arrangement
so two things about this picture
you can see that the arrangement is how
information passes between interfaces
you can kind of see it visually
but two things about this will be
generalized
first the information sharing can be
much messier you don't all you don't
except in a circuit you don't just have
perfect wires
the inputs here might be affected by all
sorts of stuff and second the
information sharing can change
like the interfaces can change shape i
might close my eyes but also the thing i
say to you might change your inner
interaction so i'm that's contained in
this notion of an arrangement
um
so formally if you do know category
theory then you've probably heard of
categories functors and natural
transformations and polynomials are in
fact functors from set to set and an
arrangement it looks like this picture
but all i mean by it is a natural
transformation of polynomials so every
one of these pictures can be translated
into a natural transformation of
polynomial functors
and uh what this picture would be is you
take the little arrangement uh little
interfaces p1 p2 p3 p4 p5 you would
tensor them together
and then you the arrangement itself
would be a natural transformation from
p1 tensor p2 tension p5
to q the outer outer
interface here
now what's happening so brief interlude
for meta stuff i just told you that an
arrangement is natural transformation of
polynomial functors
and all that's category theory and i'm
not expecting you to know category
theory i'm not expecting the audience to
know category three so what's up with
why why would i even tell you um that
stuff i'm just trying to show you what
the math looks like let any technical
person in the audience who does know
category theory see that i'm what i'm
talking about and kind of know where to
look for what's next
but for everyone else or everyone
i just want to show what the math looks
like and what it's about because so much
of math is quantitative
or maybe it's about shapes or something
but this map is really different so i
want you to see it because i want you to
ask like what is how is this math and
what is it for and the point is it's
about interfaces it's about how you
manipulate them how you arrange them how
you nest them and interfaces have
outputs and inputs and they're captured
that can depend on the outputs and that
sort of structure is kind of hard to
talk about cleanly but it's really well
captured with polynomials
not considered as functions but as like
ways of holding structure and then you
can do these operations to the
polynomials and they get they let you
make new interfaces from old
and we'll be talking about arrangements
and dynamics next but again they'll just
be in this category of polynomial
functors
that um it's all kind of the same story
again and again we don't have to change
our accounting system to move between
interfaces arrangements nesting dynamics
etc
okay so dynamics let's look at this
arrangement again what if every pi all
these p's had a dynamical system running
it well then what i'm saying here is
that q therefore would too
so a dynamical system is a thing with
states that evolved through time
uh my current emotional state or the
state of like where i think i am in the
talk or whatever is my current state and
then i look at you guys and i see what
you're looking like or i read the slide
and then it changes and then i
um
i output something so that's what a
dynamical system is
and then it can be formalized as a
system of odes or or a discrete
dynamical system or you can just think
of it as a high level idea
um
and i've said this so many times now but
i'll say one more time you're in a state
that shows up as your position
in other words your output and then any
possible input you get would change your
state
and right so the math could be discrete
or continuous it both works in this
polynomial setup
so mathematically a dynamical system 1p
is a natural transformation
s y to the s to p
where s is the set of states and again
why am i telling you this because all
the math looks the same whether you're
talking about arrangements as natural
transformations between polynomial
functors or you're talking
about dynamical systems themselves
inhabiting these interfaces they're all
just natural transformations between
polynomial functions
and then
given the arrangement of all these p's
inside of q
which is a natural transformation
and giving this now transformation here
that puts the dynamics in each of them
you get the dynamics in q
so phpi had a dynamical system in it so
would q
by composing natural transformations
so this is the currently the last math
slide
um
i want to think about dynamics a bit
more so if you remember a few slides ago
i was talking about operations
in a dynamical system on p plus q
would be one that can switch between p
mode and q mode so sometimes you're
outputting p stuff and inputting from it
sometimes you're outputting q stuff
and inputting from that
sorry i'm a little bit sick so my voice
is not great today
um a dynamical system on p times q would
output both simultaneously in any state
it's outputting both but we can receive
from just one or the other
a dynamical system on p tensor q would
output both and receive from both
a dynamical system on p composed q would
be would do the serial protocol where it
outputs a p
and outputs a strategy for taking any
input on p and send and turning it into
an output on q and then it would listen
for
an input on p and an input on q so kind
of just tells you here's what i'm going
to do no matter what you i mean it gives
you a serial protocol is what i'm saying
and what about p
inner hom q this is the
in the category polynomials functors
there is a internal harm for tensor you
may have absolutely no idea what i'm
talking about but it's something that
comes with the math that no one created
it it wasn't invented it just is part of
the structure kind of like the complex
numbers are miraculous in the sense that
you um
you say you want algebraic closure and
all of a sudden you get
you get if i have one derivative then i
have all derivatives and stuff like that
so it's kind of the category of
polynomial functors is kind of
miraculous it has tons and tons of
structure that no one asked it to have
it just hasn't
but what is this structure this internal
harm
well it's the sort of thing that runs
arrangements for p and q
so a dynamical system on this thing
where i tensor p 1 p 2 p 3 p 4 p 5 comma
q and put it in brackets this internal
harm
what it does
it's a dynamical system
this is a polynomial even though it
looks like a big expression it's itself
a polynomial
and this polynomial has outputs and has
inputs as usual and so what a dynamical
system on this would do is would be
output arrangements it output okay now i
want you to wire to you and you to wire
to you and you do wire to you so if
you're forming an institute you'd say
wow uh let's have uh this guy report to
that person and all that sort of stuff
and you would create some arrangement
and then that's what you output as the
ceo say
and then you listen and you see what
flows on the wires and you see how alice
is talking to bob and how bob is talking
to carla and all that stuff and you'd
listen to that and as you listen you'd
say hey actually
i want bob to report to carla instead of
alice or whatever and so you would
change the arrangement your inner
internal state would be to listen
and receive
the stuff that's flowing on the wires
and you'd be affected by that and then
you'd output new arrangements for the
system and i think that's kind of
getting to this morphology thing uh
maybe maybe there are systems that are
monitoring
the the source of transmissions that are
happening between subsystems and then uh
and then
outputting new ways that they should
arrange each other
okay so let me give some applications
digital circuits and control systems fit
neatly here
so a computer is a nested arrangement of
dynamical systems
every transistor the dynamical system
and two of them make up a nand gate not
end
and then you can get an or gate by
wiring together three nand gates like
this so i've taken my inputs and i split
them and i feed them to the nand into
the nand and then i put them together
and i put them into the nand and now i
have or
and this whole thing
is just like nand has two inputs and one
output this whole thing has two inputs
and one output but it's got some
internal structure
and now we've got an or gate we could
nest or gates and and gates and nand
gates and we can get
adder circuits and multiplying circuits
and
alus arithmetic
units whatever
and um
and cpus and monitors and they're all
made just with transistors
um
like the memory cells are all
are all like flip-flops or just
situated transistors and so we can kind
of make this nested system of
transistors
and get a computer and so the
arrangement here is all really simple
um it's never changing in time it's
soldered in it's fixed
unlike us on the zoom call its dynamics
are simple every state is just a
function of the input only and it it
just uses there's no memory in the in
the transistors and yet because of loops
in the wiring in the arrangement we get
um all possible things that the computer
can do
so with enough nesting and enough um
interesting arrangements you even though
the arrangements internally are not that
difficult when you nest them they get
really
amazing in the sense you get a computer
and that is the dynamical system that is
happening right now allowing for this
zoom call to take place
i guess there's some internet stuff too
that i don't know how it's made but the
computers are made this way
um control systems also have complicated
dynamics let's say this is a power plant
or something but again i'm i think they
basically have fixed arrangement so your
cruise control in your car
isn't changing whether it's listening to
the gas or the
um maybe for the battery in a hybrid car
there be a changing arrangement but at
least
old-fashioned control systems have a
fixed arrangement of how the feedback's
going to work to control the um
the speed or whatever temperature
um deep learning also fits into the
formalism of polynomial functors but in
a different way here the interfaces are
all the same they're all outputting a
real and inputting a real
um
now and the arrangements are all really
simple they're activated weighted sums
now i i'm drawing this differently than
most people would most people would put
these three boxes on the left
of this big box
um and they'd wire the three things in
and it would seem like this was a box
taking r3 to r
the way i'm
thinking about
because i want to put this into the
context of this accounting system of
polynomial functors it works better to
think about
a neuron listening to some neurons on
his left or some predecessor things so
like a higher level thing listening to
lower level things
it makes more sense formalism to put
them inside
um
and then the arrangement isn't just a
fixed isn't just a wiring diagram but it
has more structure as i said those
wiring diagrams were just easy cases um
often it's more complex but they're
still arrangements in the sense of
natural transformations of polynomial
functors
and what this arrangement would do is it
take the output of these sub guys and
weight them maybe multiply this one by
3.2 etc add them up and then do an
activation function and output that to
the higher level bigger thing
then when it gets a loss in it would
take the gradient and pass the
components of that gradient to the three
um
uh or past the components of that loss
to the three things and then take the
gradient
and change the wiring diagram not the
wiring but the interaction pattern so it
would change these three numbers
so the information flowing out is the
inner box's current guess about what's
going on in the world the current
weighted sum
is like the these guys send out their
guesses we add them up we send out our
guests as the higher level manager here
and then we get some loss function we
distribute it to our sub units we also
use it to change the arrangement
um here so
this the changing of weights in the
training of a neural network
is the uh is the changing arrangements
that i've been kind of pushing
this whole time
um right the arrangement is dynamic the
loss
not only is sent to little boxes but is
updating the arrangement the collection
of weights
um
so deep neural networks is one of four
examples we currently have of a certain
structure that a postdoc working with
medium brandon shapiro and i are calling
a dynamic organizational structure or
dynamic opera
um it's a fractal-like system of
arrangements that change through time
where the arrangement decides how
information flows through the system
just like i've been saying and yet the
flowing information contains the
arrangement just like i've been saying
and we formalized this using category
theory and the four examples we have are
deep learning like i was talking about
in the previous slide
prediction markets um
hebbian learning so this is with sophie
lipkind and non-cooperative strategic
games so we have only four examples of
this structure but i'm guessing there
are many more so i'm guessing for
example that active inference can be
another one or maybe free energy
minimization or something like that
the point is that these are like very
fractal structures where like the
a collection of deep learners or
gradient descenders if you put them
together you get another gradient
descender
if you take a bunch of predictors and
make them into a single predictor you
get another predictor
so like the collection of predictors
becomes a predictor
and the way that um
the way that predictors are
the way that wealth or trust is
distributed between predictors is
properly nested and stuff like that i
can't really go into it but uh i'm
interested in whether well i'll say that
next slide
okay so wrapping up kind of many people
think of math about number but it's not
a math subject an accounting system
tracks certain things
and what we're trying to track above is
dynamic arrangements math is called
polynomial functors and it's well known
in beloved in category theory and it
accounts for interfaces dynamics and
arrangements in a really nice way
and it's about building a bigger system
from little littler parts
it accounts for composing circuits and
control systems and deep learning and
prediction markets
and then you could combine these because
they're all in one formalism you could
take your control system and hit hook it
up to a deep learning system and put
that in a prediction market and
you all of it's just polynomial
functions all the way down
i think it might have
maybe i should have said might have
particular value in active inference
uh
because it lets us talk coherently and
precisely about these things like
changing interfaces i
i might be wrong but i don't know that
that's a part of
the formalism of active inference today
um in terms of like changing the
arrangement and stuff like that but i'm
interested to hear more
you guys
um changing how things communicate
change how the communication pattern
itself changes as information is
exchanged
but if we wanted to make active
inference into a dynamic organizational
structure for example
um
you might like uh
dynamic organizational structure one
person when they saw that they thought
oh
you should really call it multi-scale
dynamic organizational structure in
order to really clarify your particular
brand here um but uh maybe not so
especially so what would we do if we
wanted to make free energy minimization
a dynamic organizational structure well
we would specify all the interfaces that
we're going to be talking about that
would be used to house free energy
minimizers like what is a free energy
minimizer allowed to output and what are
they allowed to input
and you would get clear on that as step
one and then you would consider how free
energy minimizers arrange themselves
like what an arrangement of free energy
minimizers would be
where if you arrange them in that way
it would constitute a larger scale free
energy minimizer
so that's the sort of thing you would
have to ask to make this into a dynamic
organizational structure and as long as
they all cohere nicely
there's some formal check we would do we
would have a dynamic organizational
structure
so to summarize
i feel like i've said it a million times
now but applied category theory is math
for tracking interlocking structures
cohering structures it's not about how
much of something there is it's about
how it's arranged
and it applies in quantum mechanics and
computer science and math and material
science and linguistics but it focuses
on structural questions in each one it
allows the content to be something that
someone else handles later and it's just
telling you how you're going to be
handling that content so that you don't
kind of step on each other's toes as you
um as you use it
so i'm interested i'm interested in the
structure of interacting dynamical
systems like how i want to account for
be able to account for this
i don't want to necessarily give the
account
but i want to be able to account for
this stuff that we're doing here
together how we change how we're
inputting you know i'm changing by
turning the speaker off or disconnecting
and therefore not inputting the same or
how we're outputting you know muting or
camera off and how all that affects what
happens on this call or wherever we are
and how we change and what we learn and
how we make sense of things together
so again i don't have specifics but what
i'm offering is this accounting system
this category of polynomial functors to
account for dynamic arrangements and i'm
hoping that it um is helpful for
thinking about active inference
so that's it happy to talk about stuff
that's super awesome david thank you so
much um i
have a million questions but i didn't
want to interrupt because i was really
enjoying just
hearing you um
because it like helps it gel more
solidly in my brain if you can
if the interaction is like give me all
the things and then let me like pick
apart the little pieces and maybe that
works for hopefully the audience also
uh danielle did you are you watching the
youtube chat is there questions no do
you want to go before i go because i'll
interrogate him for a while
okay and this doesn't block you does it
this thing up here
no it looks fine okay okay i moved it
seems for you to be there
lou please begin the interrogation and
i'll be ready with the live questions
soon
cool all right um okay so let me just go
back to the beginning
um so in the very beginning you said
that you feel like active inference kind
of meshes with category theory
um and i just i'm curious
as i mean i think like i kind of got a
really good idea through the course of
your talk but maybe you could articulate
the why
um to maybe kind of
help us understand
where that that basis is coming from on
your house
cool yeah
when i when i first heard it it was one
thing was like
utility and prediction are
melded
like what i want is i'm just expecting
the world to be a certain way and what i
want is for it to be that way so if i
want to
um
if i really if i really intend
to have something it's because i know
that it i kind of deserve it i can't
actually
i think people might have fantasies
where they think they can
get things they don't deserve or
something but it doesn't work out i'm
not sure i feel like i'm going into too
much there but but i like this idea of
um melding those two things because
utility never really made sense to me
uh
it's like where do i get this utility
function from
well but i really what i somehow thought
was like
like what they're saying is like my my
knees are a certain way
they're a prediction
of like the fact that gravity will be in
a certain range or my lungs can take in
this sort of or this way because they're
a prediction
that my lineage has made about what sort
of atmosphere i'm going to be put into
and um the things i'm saying to you
right now like utility whatever i'm
using to decide how good it is for me to
say a thing is my prediction of what's
what's actually wanted here
so i like that it like reduced the
number of variables there like instead
of a number of entities in the universe
or something from utility and prediction
just to prediction
um
i don't remember
like
other things exactly but i just remember
kind of feeling like oh i also like that
it's scale free so free energy
minimization for example
or or bayesian predict you know updatey
stuff doesn't need you to be at a
particular scale it's not about
subatomic particles or something i like
this scale free
and um
and that somehow it's a physics-y thing
like i'm really looking for a scale-free
thing you mentioned emergence blue and
i'm going to stop talking soon because i
know your lifestyle thing but but um
i i'm not a huge fan of the concept of
emergence because i feel like it's
usually talking assuming we're going to
start from a low level and then say
and then the next level is magic and
then they start from that level they're
like and then the next level is magic
and i'm really looking for like
the principles where
the inductive step
the move from
n to n plus one is the thing we're
monitoring so we're never like confused
we're like whoa where did this amazing
thing happen we're always seeing we're
we're monitoring that part and um
i really like that free energy
minimization
and entropy maximization and stuff like
that is the sort of thing that i could
imagine happening at all scales no
matter if you're a person or you're a
cell or you're an atom
well definitely i have to apologize for
this like beeping what's going on in my
background i'll try to remember to mute
but i i do think that like yes emergence
is cool but also there's this
bi-directional
information flow um and when we had mike
levin come on to the live stream he
really talked about it when he discussed
his paper the computational boundary of
the self so yes like there are bottom up
um there are emergent properties that
happen in a collective but there's also
top down constraints on those emergent
properties that come from the quote
higher level or maybe like larger scale
so like if we're building things up and
down there's constraints that go down
and information that comes up and you've
got to have this bi-directional
information flow to even start to think
about drawing any kind of boundary or
creating like an interface around like
the thing itself like that like we we
caught we talked about cognitive cones
mike love and i don't know if you're
familiar with that paper but yeah
um
it was cool
cool
it's something else and so i know like
you've talked with mike a lot and also
with chris fields um
and when chris came he really talked to
us about
contextuality
and he started to get into some
math that i think is maybe related to
some of the things that you were talking
about here so you talked about
operations that correspond to
interactions between sets
um and chris talked to us about two
spaces and like channel theory and as
these like interactions that transform
sets as um
infomorphisms
so like uh i i don't know if any of that
like language um speaks to to this or or
is like
it's hard for me to tell what is the
language of category theory and and what
is like the application of the category
theory to something in real life or or
that's not just you know the set of x
such that x is less than or equal to
like these kinds of math words right
right yeah so the the two spaces stuff
is definitely category theory and
relates um there's a
nice way of talking about the
relationship between um true space and
polynomial functors although i don't
have it on the tip of my tongue right
now
um
so these polynomial functors are kind of
bi-directional
because the like if you have these
arrangements which are maps of
polynomial functors
this sort of thing
this uh
quote unquote higher level thing
is talking to
the lower level things lower level
things are talking to each other and
they're also talking to the higher level
thing so there's this kind of
bi-directional thing there and so on
that level i'd say
um yes it does sound similar to what
mike uh chris fields was saying and then
but you also asked like what is the
application of category theory
um so once you have an accounting system
you can build a tool from it so if
someone says hey i got this great idea
it's all about plus and times and like
dollars can be added but not multiplied
and they can be multiplied by numbers
but not each other or whatever you make
this rule and then someone could build a
spreadsheet that
program that incorporates that rule
and
maybe current spreadsheets don't allow
you don't keep you on the rails with
respect to not multiplying two dollar
figures but you could imagine that they
they did
um so what's the application the
application is that once you have the
accounting system the mathematical
accounting system you can build tools
from it or you can just think through it
on the whiteboard or something but if
you build tools
uh let's that's a major way people use
math
um calculus or whatever they simulate
things
if you use category theory what it lets
you do is you say i have this annoyed
category called poly
and then someone says
you know they want to implement it well
instead of thinking about all the
features they want from an interface
language and they're like oh and let's
have it print like this and let's have
it publish the web like that and like
you know they have all these features
what it allows you to do is not look at
any feature requests you just implement
the accounting system you just put it in
there just the map
and you call it a day and then if
somebody else wants to add stuff you do
it later and you don't use that to
influence
kind of the basic code it allows you to
write very very highly structured and
very compressed code that does
that does all of the major
back-end work of the thing and then
every other feature request is like you
know that's kind of the gold plating or
like the thing that makes a user
interface
for it but um
does that make sense as a as an
application
yeah and like perfectly segues into my
next question actually so so you talked
about um
category theory as like a potential
accounting system and early on um even
actually i think you even mentioned
morality in your talk but even before we
were talking about intelligence and like
grounding and ethics and wisdom
and
um i'm now like in kernel studying
um regenerative finance
and potentially like new ways
to
develop like accounting systems that
maybe involve like carbon credit or some
kind of moral or ethical bound that's
like a new system for like not just plus
and minus dollars
but but maybe like a new um system for
accounting that like a ledger that that
allows
for more thoughtful consideration into
um or of like the environment and just
the world at large and humanity and our
our fate and future as a species um and
i just wonder if you've thought about
that or um and i definitely think like
you definitely think that category
theory can maybe jump in and rescue us
here or just what are your thoughts on
that
yeah so
category theory um you have to do the
work of deciding what your
accounting system is in some sense like
it helps you decide what
what things
since it has talked about all of math
um it can be written in category theory
at this point um
or at least all that i i can think of
it's got all all of math is the stuff
that people have used so far to think
about the world and so it's somehow our
getting all of that
into a single system so it's likely that
whatever we're thinking about
now with this regenerative finance etc
if
you know there would would be some good
way of putting it into category theory
but that still has to be done it won't
rescue you except it'll be there as like
yeah i think i could if i had an expert
to work with i could do it
um but then in terms of the question
itself regenerative finance and um
and that and morality and stuff like
that
one i mean i don't know if this is the
sort of thing that jumps to mind but one
thing i think in our society that might
be pretty bad
um and it's in ourselves also
or at least maybe it's good but it's
good in a way i don't understand yet
and that is um that in these big
arrangements there's little things whose
job it is to hide
the intentions of the things inside
and so um
like i think of i'm not sure
i'm gonna name this person and it's
almost a trigger but um jeffrey epstein
i think like what was he good at i kind
of think i know he was known for like
making these financial derivative
instruments that like
hid
the more the subprime mortgage stuff
i i and i feel like his whole island and
all the stuff he was doing like he just
knew all the secrets and his and i could
imagine um
backing away from him but like also like
the meat industry
there are secrets about how meat is
produced and when you go to the
supermarket their job is to make sure
you don't think about that stuff
and so um when you form these big
arrangements
or the financial system like there's a
lot of which goes on the financial
system that's hiding the
almost slavery that takes place in
various places um
so
and then in myself maybe the greed i
think all this is really coming from
the need to survive um at all costs or
something like that that
seems like our cells in our body don't
have but we somehow have gotten
um i'm not sure about that so anyway one
thing that comes to mind is like
what's up with hiding intentions and
do is there any place for that
wow
um also just like from from a very
biological perspective i do think that
we have little things inside of us
maybe because that function it is to
hide
things but i definitely don't have
access to the all of the knowledge of
every single cell in my body
right or every even organ
so so i mean like
survive at all costs like yes i could be
like knock on some wood growing a little
cancer tumor somewhere that's not known
to me and like we have mechanisms that
mask pain and that even mask like
proprio reception or
so there's a lot of things going on like
there's a lot of hiding even in bile in
the biological system that happens
between
scales which totally leads into my next
question so perfectly
which was about compression and
elaboration
um and
so so like
what is hidden
or what is compressed
right and and what is the the
relationship or function or um
utility of category theory in
elaborating compression
and elaboration like if i get the
compressed version of like what the
larger box container
is what's happening with the larger box
can i elucidate the structure and what's
happening in the smaller boxes
or the even the arrangement of the
smaller boxes in the the within the
larger container the larger scale say um
and just so so how much how how good is
this math is it gonna how how how is it
going to help me understand compression
and elaboration across scales
yeah cool um i first want to say that i
think of category theory as humanity's
best thought compression language
um
i didn't
yeah so for example the category of
polynomial functors is
the
full subcategory of functions from set
to set spanned by co-products of
representables
and now i've told you the entire
definition and i don't expect you to
understand it and i wouldn't even expect
of category theories to understand it
but i would write that expression that i
just said on the board and it would be i
don't know 20 words or 30 words
um
and then
that would be sitting there at the top
and then i would go through like what do
i mean by category what do i mean by set
what i mean by functor what do i mean by
uh spanned by what do i mean by uh
co-product and what do i mean by
representable and i would go through
those um words and i would explain
whichever ones of those you didn't
understand and then i would explain
those in a compressed way and then you'd
say yeah i get that or no i don't get
that and we could unpack this thing
so the category theory itself before we
get to your question about the
interfaces and arrangements
is is this amazing thought compression
language where all the stuff in this
talk
all the math behind it um and the stuff
is all as all an elaboration of of this
very very compressed
few words um because we really made this
language for compressing big thoughts
uh
then there if i remember i hope i'm not
missing i mean part of the question but
you're also talking about the
um arrangements themselves as
compressions
and um
and yeah like an an adder circuit is a
compression
of a bunch of
and or logic circuits that are
themselves a compression of nand gates
which are themselves
transistors arranged in a certain way a
certain way certain way and the nand
gate if you think about it why did you
arrange those two transistors that way
because you knew
that it would always act this way you
can kind of like everyone's ending
uh all the time but orr is a pretty good
thing to think about
and and is a pretty good thing to think
about and plus is pretty good and so
these compressions
out of all the possible ways of
arranging transistors
into the number of transistors in a
outer circuit that can add two
three-digit numbers or something like
that
that might i don't know let's just
pretend that took um
let's just
took a thousand transistors
if
out of all the ways of arranging a
thousand transistors there's like a few
that you would actually like
that where you're like instead of adding
two numbers and getting like some random
thing you get the actual sound
and so we compress into for some reason
some compressions are useful because we
can predict them um and like i can kind
of predict your behavior based on what
i'm seeing out of on your face
and and what you need to know from me or
what i can do to help and vice versa and
like
that ability to compress all this stuff
into just something you output on the
interface
is is really important
and the same is happening in the or gate
and the and the outer circuit and stuff
so you kind of create things that have a
well-defined usefulness even though i
have no idea what that means
and um
and
i don't know that does that answer the
question or did i miss a major part of
it
so let me just repeat a part of it
so if i am
a compression say like let me just do
something really simple i am the number
six and i'm a compression of you know
three numbers like and it could be so
can i can i
i i guess what i compress is the set of
the possible numbers that make up six
like the three like that that's what i
compress right so that's what translates
to the compression so you can never
really go
from the compression number six to
figure out which of those three numbers
were
right right
right
you can um what you do know is the
remaining thing that sickness gives you
um
there's lots of things that use six and
they're all happy to know about six
and same with or like i don't know how
you made your ore you could have made it
with 43 000 transistors and wasted a
bunch of them but like the point is
i don't need to know all that stuff all
i need to know is that this thing's
going to take to boolean and produce a
boolean
in a certain way
and so the compression this outer
interface is saying
i don't care about all your private
methods just tell me like what can i
expect from you
and i think part of like you know in our
society we have identities i'm guessing
that identity which is such a major
thing today is like this compression of
like what's expected from the person
and
um
we
we are working out like how those
identities
really do help us expect things from
each other
so just on the topic of identity and
like to follow up and maybe continue
this train of thought a little bit so
like i am blue i am a human right like
i'm a human that's alive that's here
talking under the compression of you
know math stream number 4.1 which all of
this conversation will eventually
compress to active institute math stream
4.1
but but like the fact that i am blue and
i am human like i am one among the set
of many things that is all human
and like we describe the set like living
human
in a certain way like i have a certain
number of cells
but many of the cells are not human
right like so so more cells at some
times of your
you know digestive cycle than others so
more cells sometimes are not human than
actually are human and so it's these set
of like things like how many human cells
how many you know
different e coli
how many like you know uh different
types of bacteria and microorganisms and
like all of these things compressed to
the set of like living human
i would like to be able to unravel like
what is like go from living human or
like even just find the limits of like
okay so now like too many e coli was
like some decomposing human that's not
alive
so so like i would like to be able to
really push those boundaries of or even
find the boundary of of what makes the
set of
cells that is a living human versus like
when do you it's like the phase
transition like the critical point at
what critical point are are so many of
these microorganisms alive that i become
not a living human anymore
yeah
yeah so in the same way like a an and
gate is not made out of and gates it's
made out of smaller things or you know a
logic all right so
we don't really expect the high-level
thing to be made out of little things
but the reason i think you're saying
that there are these things called human
cells is because we share this dna and
this the dna that you're tracking when
you say that hey the e coli is not me
and the bacterial gut gut bacteria stuff
is not me um because it doesn't have our
dna but it is you in the sense that it
helps you as a pattern exist and so if i
was putting an interface around you i
definitely wouldn't personally want to
like only use your dna cells and call
those you because that would be you
wouldn't be a very good you um
but uh yeah so what can happen is like
these e coli or these cancers or
whatever inside of you let's say you're
this gigantic arrangement of stuff
um
that what can happen is that they can
start to say things
that um start to mess with that
arrangement and start to change the
arrangement so remember the arrangement
is changing based on what's flowing
through the wires so your e coli things
in there might be saying some stuff or
spreading some stuff that's changing the
arrangement and now this cell is no
longer talking about cell when it should
have and now that it's no longer talking
to that cell because the arrangement has
changed now it's now that other cell is
not receiving what it usually does so it
starts to say different things and
slowly this um
this changes the arrangement so much
that you're no longer a cohering whole
and the the things that we can expect
from you your identity has changed to
one that's like
not as interesting
definitely and so can you see that in
the with the math like where this maybe
phase transition takes place or like at
what level of rearrangement like maybe
it's 20 rearrangement or like you know
20 incoherent arrangement or
measure like the information in the
circuit transferring from one to
like from from one piece to another such
that like when the information flow is
so disrupted then it like ceases to be a
functional arrangement
yeah i
i think that problem is as hard as like
being able to look at a spreadsheet and
seeing if there's corruption
like people can do it but it's a
judgment it's like someone decides like
no that's not
that's not real
um
or yeah it's like i know it when i see
it kind of thing so
there might be rules of thumb you could
create in this accounting system like
uh but i doubt
i don't feel comfortable creating like
the
the definition of the faith transition
and i wouldn't expect it to be
any more than a judgment but
yeah
cool thank you and thanks for letting me
kind of um ramble on a little bit there
uh
so on this slide while we're here this
is totally changing the subject
um if you were roman
like if you were ancient roman using
ancient roman numerals
would hindi arabic numerals still be
empirically better
or does that depend on context i think
they would
i i know that it might not be
in the current culture but i think it i
think it is just empirically better um
like in the sense
like is a better baseball player better
well they're better at baseball
um
like i'm not saying that's better like
maybe you just love these things and it
makes you feel really good to see exes
and stuff and then for you like it's
great like use this thing but if you
want to be a math person that multiplies
things like you
apparently in rome like they were they
knew about square root of two back then
they figured out like
1.414 apparently i don't know i don't
know if that's true but they were
pythagoras was like back then like can
you imagine taking square roots if this
is what you're using it's just
you can barely multiply like how could
you take e to a power and do
could we do um quantum mechanics today
if we were having to do this
could we do
could we do even compound interest with
this
like i would never ever want like i
would
so it just wins like it just
it's empirically better because those
who decide to move to this system will
out compete these
and um in life
there is some sort of competition
and um
so i i do think that it's empirically
better
but i'm happy to hear if you disagree
i mean i do think like you know survival
of the fittest right so so
clearly like the hindi arabic numerals
have have won
but but also um i think that if i had
never seen a hindi arabic numeral before
and was trying to multiply that like i
would prefer because it's like just what
i'm familiar with it's part of my
model is to use these roman numerals if
i was in ancient rome that would and i
would be like what is this one for you
know and so it's just whatever i guess
that you're you're familiar with but but
it's it's um
neat to hear your perspective also
um
i mean like if you were a moth and it
was turning you know there this the
everything was turning brown because of
new smoke
you might be familiar with being a white
moth but like any moth that changed to
being a brown moth would win
um i don't know yeah there's familiarity
and that is a thing because we need that
we need homeostasis and stuff but
there's
i don't know yeah i i think that if
someone was a more capable person in
terms of being able to change
they would
they would appreciate that faculty in
themselves like they'd be like ah i'm
glad i tried
to change yeah
well and so now i have a series of
questions about um
the interface and the dynamics and
interactions i don't know if you want to
skip forward to those slides so are
these are these like terms like you said
you had some key terms interface
dynamics interaction arrangement um and
i'm tracking
um these terms are they part of
like the formalism of category theory is
this something that like everyone is a
category they're studying they're not
okay so so that was my my question was
um you know
because the way that you
discussed these interfaces positions
forces states arrangements enclosures
really spoke to active inference so much
which is why like i really get why
you're like oh yeah that seems to like
kind of mesh with my current ideas um
like so like we have the interface
which uh we talk about as like a markov
blanket like a separation a boundary um
and in the markov blanket are like the
sense states and the action states so
like in the interface it is like you
would call it positions
and forces like that's where i act on
the world and the world acts back on me
like in the the markov boundary um and
and so similarly like you talked about
like the dynamics of a system as being
hidden and only like
internal to the system and we have like
hidden states like your internal states
um and then yeah the interaction is like
what i would refer to as like maybe a
state update
like so so there's like you know we
interact and then i might change or i
might it might just influence my future
trajectory so i just wanted to like
highlight the great degree of similarity
between
what you talked about and like what we
talk about very regularly and active
inference great so what i did was i took
i i started noticing polynomial
functions wanted to do what i was trying
to do
and then
i took the feeling of using them like
when i the intuition i get by asking
myself what a map of polynomial functors
is or whatever
and came up with these words as the
things that most trap like most
intuitive english words that tracked how
the math was was changing or how the
math like
developed as i made a story about these
things so these are really just the
words that i
found to most
give me intuition for tracking what the
math was was doing automatically
it looks like daniel has his hand raised
oh yeah thank you just great
questions blue and david thanks for the
very
powerful and creative talk i think on
this topic of the active inference
uh ontology mapping i think that was
really
quite well stated which is this idea of
an input output system
or an interface
and things that are on one side of the
interface are shielded from that on the
other side of the interface otherwise
quite literally it would be a different
thing
it's a really powerful idea and it comes
up in computer science with apis it
comes up in graphs and topology
and we can even think about things like
the arithmetic operations
like order of operations or nested
parentheses it's like well what happens
in the parentheses it stays in the
parentheses until it's compressed and
then it goes into some other area and
then also even how you describe
searching for intuitive words and i'm
sure actively inferring with many
learners
for terms that have a natural
interpretation
or a conversational interpretation
and also point towards
more technical
um usage which i think in active
inference we see a lot about system
delineation and partitioning from the
environment like such as the ones that
you've brought up nested systems and
interacting systems
and also regarding some numerical
quantities like surprise attention and
so on
although also we have recently seen some
symbolic active inference
implementations
from jf klossier
that are engaging in this action
perception loop
without sending statistical or numerical
messages but rather communicating about
uh logic values
so i just wanted to note that and uh
if you have any thoughts otherwise i'll
read a question from the chat
um yeah a quick thought is like somehow
when i we take language for example math
and we
translate it into
motion so like if you say please pass
the salt then like 10 to the 15 atoms
will move through space
you know you say this word in language
and then 10 to the 15 atoms move through
space and like some salt crystals land
on your
on your um
food or whatever and so
by having the math attached into
intuitive ideas in our in our minds
we can then take the mathematical ideas
and translate them into the movement of
atoms so like me being able to talk or
or whatever and like it's really
important that we have intuitive ways of
thinking about these things because
otherwise they won't translate down into
the movement of atoms that actually the
action that we see in the world that
actually
uh accomplishes anything
so i'm i'm i'm worried about all the
mathematicians that are doing math that
they don't have any sense at all about
how it could ever be used
and this is kind of the point of topos
institute is like
you can i don't mind if you do like okay
you can do whatever you want but like i
don't see a point in doing math if you
have no idea how that would ever
be useful to anyone even in a thousand
years
and so i'm i'm
i don't know so yeah to connect the
point is like to connect with the
audience here have this possibly be
useful to anyone for real
i need to find the words that take the
math and translate it into intuitive
concepts so that they can come back to
the math if they want to or whatever
blue anything to add on that
um
go ahead and uh read the chat questions
great
all right so this will pull us back
generalized a little bit and then i'm
sure we could talk more active inference
or
institute talk
so ali wrote
it is said that category theory is the
most abstract area of mathematics out
there perhaps we can even call it a kind
of meta mathematics
daniel dennett claims in intuition pumps
and other tools for thinking that we can
theoretically go meta
on every level of abstraction
so
is it possible to conceive a level of
abstraction even more meta than category
theory in mathematics
yeah great question um
so
there is a category of all categories
there is
the thing is that when you have a
category of all categories first of all
it's like
really big
and second of all um
it has an even higher level structure
than each category does so it's called a
two category of all categories and then
there's a three category of all two
categories
and there but there is amazingly a thing
called infinity categories that finishes
this thing where there's an infinity
category of all infinity categories and
i think
i think that that the abstract like it's
very hard to think about this thing
but um and it's still an active area of
of research to create like a nice
infinity category
um
but the but yeah people keep getting
stuck on hey i've got this category i've
got all these categories and i want
something more abstract in it and then i
needed two category and i ah i'm done i
got the two category of all categories
but then eventually someone wants the
next one and so um
so yeah this is this is a great question
and there's an active area of research
right now
okay interesting i'll ask one
active inference related question that
connects also to enclosures and nesting
so
we've
in the generative models that we see in
active inference they're bayesian graphs
and they're describing control systems
and action perception loops and so on
we've seen
nested models be used in
at least two different ways
one is to describe systems who are
physically nested within one another
such as an organism and then the organs
the cells the organelles and those
interfaces and what that nesting or
enclosing
can be interpreted as has a natural
spatial interpretation
however there have also been nested
models
of cognitive
modeling flavors
and in those cases it's never been clear
whether the nesting or enclosing that's
happening
is reflecting spatial boundaries
in some cognitive space if one chooses
that direction of interpretation or in
fact what that nesting entails
and then importantly why it would have a
structural isomorphism with the nesting
of the matruska and just things that are
physically nested inside of each other
so what does nesting and enclosure
mean here and is it referring to spatial
boundaries or other conceptual
boundaries
yeah great so um
this uh so like same with airplanes or
something you have the physical airplane
but then
different parts of the airplane are
really talking to each other that may
not be like the the radio of the control
tower and the radio of the airplane or
in some sense more closely connected
than the radio of the airplane and the
engine of the airplane
the the radio of the airplane and the
radio and the pilot are strongly
connected
and so yeah there's always this logical
what i would call physical arrangement
and logical arrangement
and those might be different
but what they are from this point of
view
um
or one thing you could do
is just so if you if you look at i don't
know this x12 and x21 you might imagine
that there's a logical way of arranging
things where these really seem like
they're quite close
and so
uh
i probably should have shown this but
that picture is the same as this one
i've just undone the nesting
let's see if i can try to show that
so
yeah let's see this is oh no it's not
what
oh i've darn it i didn't take the same
one that's confusing
okay well i think i added an extra loop
on this thing or something
anyway my point is we can undo this
nesting
and have it be
have this one be closer to this one and
some other nesting
so you could use
this organizational system called an
operad to handle the fact that you might
want to nest things differently for
different purposes
this picture here is supposed to be
either
physical arrangement or logical
arrangement it doesn't matter
and it's really just about who's talking
to who that's the most important thing
the thing is that in your liver in your
brain in your cell maybe
the latency of communication is much
better than across
the boundaries
sorry for the
voice issue well very um interesting and
in neuroscience it speaks to the
distinctions of structural functional
and effective connectivity
which
if only it was dominoes hitting each
other and they were all identical but
even in that case i don't think they
would be identical so we're dealing with
something and that's a great example
with the informational and the causal
connectivity after all the bayesian
causal graph architecture is
pointing towards something that is
presenting itself as cause
with a technical specific definition
although a natural word and so it is
interesting when the causal architecture
may not reflect the physical
architecture and vice versa
right and this the opera the notion of
opera which i never said during the talk
but
this nesting thing is
[Music]
is designed to allow you to rearrange
how you want to consider inside and
outside or whether you want to consider
physical or logical
to to allow you to do that zooming on
your own time or in your way in your own
way
without affecting what the thing is
going to do as a whole
thank you blue
so just to add on to the possible layers
of nesting there's also the layer of
temporal nesting right so things happen
at like a very fast pace that we don't
observe like the light is flickering as
long as it's like greater than 60 hertz
i don't see it flickering but i know
it's flickering um and as long as it's
like not
in my perceptible range then it doesn't
really matter to me so so there's um
and just similarly like i don't think
biological evolution
maybe cares all that much about math
stream 4.1
but cares about like you know how many
children we each have and you know all
these other things right so um
that that the the relevance the salience
and
across temporal skills is also
um something to think about um and we
talked about like the changing interface
i think you mentioned that um
and with with the question of like i
don't know if active inference does this
changing interface well so it's it does
in um the markup kernel which we just
actually like learned about and talked
about when we were talking about quantum
systems with uh chris and mike and um
john
so that was like i think live stream
number
40.
also on on that technical note i would
suggest that the plain essence of the
blanket definition does not entail
any sort of dynamical rearrangement
however recent work by dalton s and
others has pointed towards the
definition of a blanket index which
reflects a weekly mixing dynamical
interface zone
that is on a zero to one continuum and
that may point towards the kind of
rearrangeable interfaces
although not with the kind of
um category theoretic nature as far as i
know but again this is like a very
interesting
area
um and i i can see many
applications in systems including online
teams and organization and so i really
liked that you
used what was that hands
um an i
for making some of these
connections
clear
cool
and just just one last connection uh you
had mentioned your applied um
[Music]
applied uh like trails that you're
chasing right now and you mentioned
prediction markets
and i do think that um well well first
of all you talked about like
um before you talked about that you
talked about the free energy minimizers
right like so if each little component
in the system is a free energy minimizer
and how like within the fvp it can um
scale to form like a container free
energy free energy minimizer so yes and
that like will stay a free energy free
energy minimizer as long as it decreases
the free energy of all of the components
in the container for it to stay a
container right so that like speaks to
self-assembly and perhaps morphogenesis
um
and then in these uh
so yeah consider how free energy
minimizers arrange themselves there we
go and how they constitute a larger
scale free energy minimizer if it lowers
the free energy um and then just in
terms of application uh prediction
markets i think is a really good
way to maybe align category theory with
the fep and i think
some of that has been done
i want to say like the multi-armed
bandit
problem is maybe like like a rudimentary
example of that and i don't remember
which live stream that was it was a long
time ago but um we did have a
a paper dealing with the multi-armored
bandit problem and using active
inference to solve it and that might be
like a way to start to align
more
on the um just on the uh prediction
market area and then david really
curious to hear what you think
i see a lot of parallels with what you
described about transistors
again you said a thousand pieces
components in this transistor
the space of the 1000 pic
n connections
might be vast and so that's where like
selective processes and abductive logic
come into play with this two-stroke
engine of like diversifying and
exploring the space and pruning down
based upon function and so we could
imagine prediction markets where
the nest mate level the the the colony
participant is making great predictions
but then they're being compiled in a way
that's actually
inadequate we could also imagine the
other extreme where no nest mate knows
how much food the colony has or what the
weather is outside etc
but
its natural actions still participate in
a colony or in a market
that makes adaptive decisions so in that
structuring of multi-scale sense making
the composability
and the ability to
create systems that are
valid across scales
and don't
enforce any kind of
implausible constraint
it becomes essential because people
point sometimes to wisdom of crowds and
all these other related areas
and there's probably some areas and some
ways of doing it that are just
incredibly effective and i'm sure we can
think of
crowds and ways of doing it and
questions where it is just not that way
yeah so in this
in this work of on
dynamic organizational structures
there's a kind of fractal-like nature to
it where the same thing like there's one
formula for the whole thing
and so in order to be
one of these things
like in this technical sense that we
wrote up um it can't have all sorts of
crazy stuff at one level that doesn't
exist at another level
it would like we
this is not supposed to be an indictment
of it but we tried to make a more
socialist example of a prediction market
um where the wealth
the the
the updated wealth would be
um more evenly uh distributed and it
wasn't hierarchy like it didn't um
it didn't have the fractal-like property
where it what would happen at the high
level was coherent with what was
happening to low level and so it could
have been because we weren't um
we weren't creative enough or whatever
but my main point is that
there are there are rules to this system
that say when it's going to kind of
align across the entire structure and
when it does then you get a very short
description
that that happens at all scales
and so
what what this kind of tracking system
allows is to to say
i mean you don't have to trust that
dynamic organizational structures are a
good system but if you were like well we
need some something to guide us here
then um you could use it to say
well this way of assembling predictions
to make a higher level prediction just
doesn't work as one of these dynamic
organizational structures and therefore
we're going to deny it as the way we're
going to do stuff because they're just
not going to work when we do multi-scale
things
these four examples
uh
do so in heavy learning for example what
we what we mean by that is um spike time
dependent plasticity where like what
happens if if i hear you say the same
kind of valence as as me but you said it
like one second ago whereas i'm saying
it now
then then i want to wire to you more
strongly so this kind of like just you
know this kind of time horizon where i'm
listening for your you know your
agreement with me and if you did before
me then i want to wired you more that
itself there is a way of putting those
together
that has this kind of fractal-like
structure but there's tons of ways of
doing it that don't
and so that that's kind of what's going
on here
in in what you just said with a short
description across scales
i see it reflected in that definition
you wrote up on the chalkboard that
could be uncompressed
and in past the salt
or past the salt police
and then in the organizational setting
that kind of multi-scale decision making
and ability to address
a
kind of integrated
stack
of scales
such that there is a compression
like
i am running
which is describing a coherent set of
actions
ranging all the way down to the to the
cellular and molecular
that can be semantically compressed in a
verbal or linguistic community
in a certain way and there's other
people who you say i'm running and
they're going to look at you like what
language are you speaking so it still is
contextual yet we can have these
multi-scale descriptions
and then i have a note from kevin in the
chat
in case it hasn't been noted might be
worth mentioning to david that markov
blankets inactive inference are just a
kind of bayesian network directed
acyclic graphs with probabilities
assigned to the vertices for all those
who will be following this trail and
working to um
build this relationship hopefully
between category theory and active
inference thank you kevin
cool thanks
so very cool i think we're coming up on
time uh david do you want to tell us
maybe a little bit about or if you have
any questions for us about active
inference we would be happy to
maybe attempt to elaborate um or also if
you want to tell us a little bit about
topos institute and um what your goal
and function or how you came to you know
self-assemble in the in that form that
would be great
well sure yeah um
basically in in academia there's no
i
my co-founder brendan and i wrote a
textbook there's no interest in textbook
writing in academia i especially like to
help people learn a new subject
there's no reward for it there's no
reward in math for
making tools out of the math or like
trying to help people either learn it or
use it and so um
basically i'd been at mit for eight
years and then my department had said
uh we now have a new policy that you can
only be here five years if you don't
have tenure and i didn't have tenure i
was a research scientist and so he gave
me two and a half years
to
to go
and so um
uh
i was like well okay that makes sense
because academia doesn't care about you
know um
about the stuff that i'm really trying
to do and so brendan and i made topos
institute because we actually want the
stuff we're doing to help the world make
more sense of things like we are this
gigantic we you know we
we're a network of people that the world
that has to steer that has to decide is
climate change real you know is
is obama a muslim we don't know these
answers apparently we don't we can't
figure these things out and that just i
think it's because we don't have the
communication to to um
to
to do that
and so i just want like i think there's
just it's not because i think there is
this greed thing in everyone or this
need to survive or whatever it is this
hiding of information that like
is probably causing problems and i don't
really understand it and you're right
like we don't need everything out in the
open
but mostly i think what's really causing
problems is just lack of communication
it's like my greed if i understood how
it's affecting you maybe i wouldn't need
to do this particular one and like if
you understood how the scientists came
to the idea of climate change and you
could like track
track that to the level you wanted to
you could like
actually you know understand these
things then maybe you wouldn't question
it it's just that like you haven't done
the experiment for yourself and you're
not trusting that it's done the right
way and so i was hoping at least that
the more we can help people communicate
and understand each other
um and have high fidelity accounting
systems so we can like be accountable
um
the more we can solve problems together
and like since that wasn't being
rewarded in academia itself
um we we needed to
go outside and position ourselves kind
of between academia and industry and
society and
so that's how we decided to form
topos
that that notion of accountable
communication
is really powerful
because we see cases where
communications are accounted for with
meta data logging and peer review and
where are we accountable socially where
is it a digital accountability
and the accounting schemes are askew and
so people are looking at their shred of
the spreadsheet
and
uncertain on how those numbers were
derived whether it's the whole picture
do you have all the sheets in that file
like with a partial picture and yet the
space of
communication strategies just like that
thousand part transistor board was vast
well there's more than a thousand people
and so the space of communication
simply edges let alone
quality and tone and content is so vast
that
again it emphasizes the need for a
vocabulary and a grammar and a syntax of
composable dynamic organizational
structures
so we can even begin to be working not
just in this one very local potentially
reason in organizational space
yeah i totally agree i mean in computers
and the internet we have
very composable things that you can
write really make math out of and like
at every scale in some sense there's the
same sort of thing happening and this
allows computer scientists to talk to
each other and the guy working someone
working on like internet protocols and
someone working on transistors on some
level they can kind of talk but like an
urban planning person
and a you know a biologist geneticist
and a mathematician and like i don't
know
whatever like these people across
society they have they're like talking
in wingdings at each other like they're
just like you know
mailbox envelope ampersand and like they
don't understand what each other is
talking about and that they're we're
never gonna
if we can't cohere like there's all
these little languages and they're not
coherent together and in category theory
there's tons of languages there's a
language of topology there's a language
of algebra there's language of logic
there's logic you know there's
number theory there's tons and tons of
languages and each one
needs to be an isolated like needs to
have its own space so it can develop
notation for itself so it can develop
techniques for itself and not have to
like ask anybody else's permission
and what category theory and same with
like urban planning and genetics like
they don't the geneticist doesn't want
to say like oh sorry i used the word you
know structure and i know you're already
using the word structure so we'll call
it something else like they don't want
to like have to do that
and yet in category theory what it
allows you to do in math is
take topology and make an analogy with
number theory or with algebra and
actually send information that can
lands intact because you the functor
tells you what you're expecting to keep
and what you're expecting to lose across
this connection and and anything you're
expecting keep it keeps and so what
we're hoping for is that by creating
like finding
languages that that you can use across
lots of disciplines from say
epidemiology to chemistry or whatever um
we can create single like languages and
then connect them to other languages
database languages and physics languages
and stuff like that and um allow them to
each evolve independently and create
their own independent you know notation
and techniques and yet be able to have
that interface that compressed thing
send something across the boundary to
somebody else and have it arrive intact
in a trustworthy and accountable way
awesome
well david thanks for
hanging out with us and talking to us
about category theory um and maybe come
back and talk to us some more about it
and maybe we can align deeper on on the
relationship between um the type of
things that you're discussing and active
inference that'd be great that's great
yeah thanks a lot for the invitations to
be with you guys today
great thanks thank you david goodbye
bye
you